Bess Lomax Hawes collection
American Folklife Center, Library of Congress
- Series II: Sound recordings, Note: Track lists and other documentation exist for some sound recordings, and can be found in Series I, box 31.
  - Subseries B: Sound cassettes, Note: SR072-SR087 are likely recordings for an ethnomusicology course taught by Hawes at SFVSC.
    - Cook Islands #3, 1992, Rarotonga religious music, 2nd Sunday. (Tape-id AFC 2014/008: SR060)
    - Cook Islands #4, 1992, Festival stage (small) and hotel. (Tape-id AFC 2014/008: SR061)
    - Cook Islands #5, 1992, Festival, daytime sites. (Tape-id AFC 2014/008: SR062)
    - Cook Islands #6, 1992 (Tape-id AFC 2014/008: SR063)
    - Cook Islands #7, 1992 (Tape-id AFC 2014/008: SR064)
    - Cook Islands #9, 1992 (Tape-id AFC 2014/008: SR065)
    - Tamburitza [Slonina], 1992 (Tape-id AFC 2014/008: SR066)
    - Arthur Galbraith Memorial, circa 1993 (Tape-id AFC 2014/008: SR067)
    - "Taking a Breath" Bess Hawes keynote address, 1994, New York Folklore Society, 50th Annual Fall Conference. (Tape-id AFC 2014/008: SR068)
    - Bess Lomax Hawes, Voices, January 15, 2000, At Oregon Historical Society, Portland, OR; Tape 1 of 2, listening copy. (Tape-id AFC 2014/008: SR069)
    - Bess Lomax Hawes, Voices, tape 2 of 2, January 15, 2000, At Oregon Historical Society, Portland, OR; Tape 2 of 2, listening copy. (Tape-id AFC 2014/008: SR070)
    - Alan Jabbour 1, circa 2003 (Tape-id AFC 2014/008: SR071)
    - 2/23, EM; #4, undated (Tape-id AFC 2014/008: SR072)
    - Wednesday, February 28, EM, undated (Tape-id AFC 2014/008: SR073)
    - Friday, March 2; Monday, March 5; EM, undated (Tape-id AFC 2014/008: SR074)
    - Wednesday, March 7; Friday, March 9; EM, undated (Tape-id AFC 2014/008: SR075)
    - Monday, March 12; Wednesday, March 14; EM, undated (Tape-id AFC 2014/008: SR076)
    - Friday, March 16; Monday, March 19; EM, undated (Tape-id AFC 2014/008: SR077)
    - Wednesday, March 21; Friday, March 24; EM, undated (Tape-id AFC 2014/008: SR078)
    - Monday, March 26; Wednesday, March 28; EM, undated (Tape-id AFC 2014/008: SR079)
    - Wednesday, April 4; Friday, April 6; EM, undated (Tape-id AFC 2014/008: SR080)
    - Monday, April 9; Wednesday, April 11; EM, undated (Tape-id AFC 2014/008: SR081)
    - Monday; Friday, April 13; EM, undated (Tape-id AFC 2014/008: SR082)
    - Wednesday, April 25; Friday, April 27; EM, undated (Tape-id AFC 2014/008: SR083)
    - Wednesday, [May 2]; Friday, May 4; EM, undated (Tape-id AFC 2014/008: SR084)
    - Monday, May 7; Wednesday, May 9; EM, undated (Tape-id AFC 2014/008: SR085)
    - Friday, May 11; no record Monday May 14, did melodic from tape; Wednesday, May 30, part of last lecture, undated (Tape-id AFC 2014/008: SR086)
    - Wednesday, May 16; Monday, May 21; EM, undated (Tape-id AFC 2014/008: SR087)
    - Marshall Islands top 40, undated (Tape-id AFC 2014/008: SR088)
    - Heritage tour sampler, undated (Tape-id AFC 2014/008: SR089)
    - Folk masters #1 African roots, undated (Tape-id AFC 2014/008: SR090)
    - Clyde "Kindy" Sproat, undated (Tape-id AFC 2014/008: SR091)
    - Doug and Jack Wallin undated, (Jacky Frazier); Jackero -- Doug Wallin, solo/[unaccompanied]; Golden Vanity -- [Doug Wallin] (fiddle intro) (Tape-id AFC 2014/008: SR092)
    - Down Home Dairyland; Goose Island Ramblers; "Wendy" Whitford, undated (Tape-id AFC 2014/008: SR093)
    - Down Home Dairyland, undated, Religious music/"Dutchman" polka; the very musical Bruegger family; Crying holy unto the Lord. (Tape-id AFC 2014/008: SR094)
    - Josh White, undated (Tape-id AFC 2014/008: SR095)
    - Northwest California Indian Music Project sampler, undated, Compiled by Richard Keeling; Side one -- Brush Dance songs; Side two -- Deerskin Dance songs, Flower Dance songs, and others. (Tape-id AFC 2014/008: SR096)
    - Golden Gate Quartet, Wright Brothers, undated, GG -- Stand the test in judgment -- Swing down chariot -- Jezebel (Tape-id AFC 2014/008: SR097)
    - African American NPR, Nick Spitzer, undated, Side A -- 4 echoes, Washington DC -- Watch night, Georgia Sea Islands -- Mardi Gras Indians, New Orleans; Side B -- Chantez men of Beaufort, NC; Zydeco Festival, Plaisance, LA; all produced by Nick Spitzer and Natioanl Public Radio with support from the NEA Folk Arts Program. (Tape-id AFC 2014/008: SR098)
    - Rehearsal at Library of Congress for December 20, 1940 program, and concert same date, undated, Wade Mainer, Burl Ives, Josh White, Golden Gate Quartet; Host, Alan Lomax; courtesy Bluegrass Unlimited, Inc.; Duplicate. (Tape-id AFC 2014/008: SR099)
    - Rehearsal at Library of Congress and Program, undated, December 20, 1940; Duplicate. (Tape-id AFC 2014/008: SR100)
    - Alan Jabbour dub, undated, April 22, 2003. (Tape-id AFC 2014/008: SR101)
  - Subseries III: CD-R
    - A tribute to Bess Lomax Hawes, 1992, Includes contributions from Riki Saltzman, Barry Bergey, Peggy Bulger, Nancy Nusz, Nick Spitzer, Dan Sheehy, David Roche, Ana Steele, Frank Hodsoll and Ruth Draper. (Tape-id AFC 2014/008: SR102)
- Series III: Graphic materials
  - Subseries A: Photographic materials
    - Almanac Days, circa 1940s, Includes photos of Bess Lomax Hawes, Pete Seeger, Woody Guthrie, Arthur Stern, Butch Hawes, Sis Cunningham, Millard Lampell, Chisolm Trail cast, among others. (Box-folder 32.01)
    - Pete Seeger, 1958-1964 (Box-folder 32.02)
    - SFVSC, circa 1950s-1970s, Includes official faculty photos and photos from Topanga Banjo Fiddle Contest. (Box-folder 32.03)
    - Performing, circa 1950s-1970s, Includes photos from Newport Folk Festival. People include Bess Lomax Hawes, Arlo Guthrie, Rev. Kirkpatrick, Butch Hawes and Oscar Brand, Guy Carawan, Sis Cunningham, Woody Guthrie, Millard Lampell, Pete Seeger, Alan Lomax and Arthur Stern, among others. (Box-folder 32.04)
    - Bess guitar classes, Los Angeles, circa 1950s-1996, Most photos likely from 1950s and 1960s. (Box-folder 32.05)
    - Films, circa 1960s-1970s, Includes photos of Bessie Jones ( Georgia Sea Island Singers ) and Earl Collins ( Say Old Man Can you Play the Fiddle?; includes handwritten note from Frankie Quimby, Bessie Jones's relative. (Box-folder 32.06)
    - Georgia Sea Island Singers, circa 1967-1974 (Box-folder 32.07)
    - Carter inauguration, 1977, Includes photos of Bessie Jones, Alan Lomax and Bess Lomax Hawes. (Box-folder 32.08)
    - Berkeley Folk Festival, circa 1960s-1970s, Includes photos of Sam Hinton and Leslie Hinton, in addition to a number of portraits of Bess Lomax Hawes. (Box-folder 32.09)
    - Party, San Fernando Valley State College, 1975, Spring party for Step It Down; includes photos of Bessie Jones and Bess Lomax Hawes, among others. (Box-folder 32.10)
    - Smithsonian Folklife Festival, circa 1975-1976 (Box-folder 32.11)
    - Washington -- Smithsonian, NEA, circa 1975-2000 (Box-folder 32.12)
    - American Folklife Center board of trustees, 1980 (Box-folder 32.13)
    - NEA, 1977-2000 (Box-folder 32.14)
    - Conferences, 1981-2004, Includes meetings of American Folklore Society, Fife conference, Wenner Gren conference, and Texas Folk Culture Program. (Box-folder 32.15)
    - Bess's NEA retirement party, 1992 (Box-folder 32.16)
    - National Medal of Arts family photos, 1993, Includes photos of Nick Hawes, Lisa Hawes, Anecka Mihalik, Corey Denos, Alan Lomax, Michael Mihalik, as well as Bess Lomax Hawes, among others; includes note from Ann Stock, White House Social Secretary. (Box-folder 32.17)
    - Kenyon College honorary degree, 1994, Photos taken at Kenyon College commencement, at which Bess Lomax Hawes was awarded an honorary degree. (Box-folder 32.18)
    - Bess Lomax Hawes Folklore Archive opening, 1998, At California State University, Northridge (formerly SFVSC); includes photos of Bess Lomax Hawes and Alan Dundes. (Box-folder 32.19)
    - Phenomenal Woman award ceremony, 2004, At California State University, Northridge (formerly SFVSC); includes photos of Bess Lomax Hawes speaking at ceremony. (Box-folder 32.20)
    - Trip to Hawaii and Micronesia, 1981, With Corey Denos, Bess Lomax Hawes's daughter. (Box-folder 33.01)
    - Hawaii, 1987 (Box-folder 33.02)
    - Samoa and Saipan, circa 1987-1992, Includes postcards in addition to photographs. (Box-folder 33.03)
    - Cook Islands trip, Festival of Pacific Arts, 1992 (Box-folder 33.04)
    - South Pacific, 1993, Includes letter possibly about Festival of Pacific Arts. (Box-folder 33.05)
    - Bess's balloon trip, circa 1993-1996, Includes photos of Naomi Bishop, John Bishop and Amanda Bishop. (Box-folder 33.06)
    - New Zealand trip, 1994, Includes photos of Naomi Bishop. (Box-folder 33.07)
    - Australia trip, 1995 (Box-folder 33.08)
    - Northern Ireland trip, 1996 (Box-folder 33.09)
    - Trips, 1974-1998, Includes photos taken in Canada, Alaska and the Soviet Union. (Box-folder 33.10)
    - Bess, circa 1930s-2006 (Box-folder 34.01)
    - Lead Belly, circa 1933-1934 (Box-folder 34.02)
    - Early married life and mothering, 1940s-1950s, Includes photos of Corey Hawes, Naomi Hawes, Nick Hawes, Danny Seeger, Shirley Mansell, Bess Lomax Hawes, among others. (Box-folder 34.03)
    - Cambridge to California trip, 1952 (Box-folder 34.04)
    - Topanga Canyon, circa 1950s, Includes photos of Topanga house and possibly Topanga Banjo Fiddle Contest (Box-folder 34.05)
    - Lomax family, circa 1890s-1950s, Photos mostly of family members. People include Bess Bauman Brown (Lomax), Ruby Terrill Lomax, Shirley Lomax, John Lomax Jr., John Nova Lomax, Alan Lomax, John A. Lomax, Brownie McGhee, Sonny Terry, Margaret Lomax among others. (Box-folder 34.06)
    - Lomax family, circa 1960s-2000s, Photos mostly of family members. People include Nick Hawes, Naomi Hawes, Core Denos, Jesse Denos, Lisa Smith, Shirley Mansell, John Bishop, Butch Hawes, Mike Denos, Pat Mansell, Alan Lomax, Virginia Brown, John Nova Lomax, Amanda Lomax, Isabelle Hawes, Joshua Hawes, Ornstein family members, among others. (Box-folder 34.07)
    - Baldwin (Butch) Hawes, circa 1940s-1970s (Box-folder 34.08)
    - Butch's art, sculpture, circa 1965-1973 (Box-folder 34.09)
    - Alan Lomax, circa 1930s-1990s, Includes photos of Joe Lomax, John Lomax Jr., John Lomax III, Charles Seeger, Penny Seeger, Woody Guthrie, among others; includes photos from Memphis Blues Festival in 1994. (Box-folder 34.10)
    - Alan Lomax, circa 1960s-2000s, Includes photos of Alan Lomax, Shirley Mansell, John Lomax Jr., Anna Lomax, among others. (Box-folder 34.11)
    - John A. Lomax Jr. and John Nova Lomax, circa 1960s-1970s, Includes photos of Alan Lomax, John Lomax III, Joe Lomax, Margaret Lomax, Susan Mansell, Shirley Mansell, Anna Lomax, among others. (Box-folder 35.01)
    - Corey's wedding shower, 1966, Includes photos of Corey Lomax, Naomi Lomax, Margot Slocum, Nell Rosenblum, among others. (Box-folder 35.02)
    - Lomax family reunion, New Braunfels, Texas, 1962, Includes photos of Nicholas Hawes, John Marabel Lomax, John A. Lomax, Joseph Lomax, Anne Lomax, Antoinette "Toni" Lomax, Margaret Marabel Lomax, Naomi Hawes (Box-folder 35.03)
    - Lomax family reunion, New Braunfels, Texas, 1988, Includes photos of Corey Denos, Naomi Bishop, Noah Bishop, Amanda Bishop, John Henry Faulk, Kristy Mihalik, Drew Mihalik among others. (Box-folder 35.04)
    - Lomax family reunion, Boulder Creek, California, 2000, Includes photos of members of Mihalik family, Mansell family, Hawes family, Bishop family, Denos family, among others. (Box-folder 35.05)
    - Santa Monica house, 1985 (Box-folder 35.06)
    - Trip with Shirley and Pat, Panama Canal, 1992, Includes prints and negatives, as well as small albums. (Box-folder 35.07)
    - Old friends, 1940s-1997, Includes photos of Guy Carawan, Evan Carawan, Fred Stone, Lee Hays, Tinya Seeger, Jimmy Driftwood, Wayland Hand, Toshi Seeger, Brownie McGhee, Alan Lomax, Henry Cowell, Tom Duggan, Fran Hood, Claire Bergey, Barry Bergey, Marcia Berman, Vicki Lang, among others. (Box-folder 35.08)
    - Unidentified, circa 1950s-2000s (Box-folder 35.09)
    - Shirley Mansell's family album (1 of 2), circa 1920s-1975, Includes photos of Naomi Hawes, John Lomax Jr., Joe Lomax, Margaret Marable Lomax, Chris Mansell, Susan Mansell, among others. (Box-folder 36.01)
    - Shirley Mansell's family album (2 of 2), circa 1920s-1975, Includes photos of John Lomax Jr., Mansell family members, Alan Lomax, Corey Hawes, Anna Lomax, John Nova Lomax, Bob Gordon, Chris Gordon, Mihalik family members, Shirley Lomax Mansell, Sister Virginia Margaret, among others. (Box-folder 36.02)
    - Shirley's album: weddings, birthday party, Austin (1 of 2), circa 1910s-1980s, Includes photos of John A. Lomax and Ruby Terrill's wedding, John Lomax Jr.'s wedding, Bess Lomax and Butch Hawes's wedding, Naomi Hawes and John Bishop's wedding, Tom Duggan and Shirley Mansell's wedding; Alaska cruise; Tom's birthday. (Box-folder 36.03)
    - Shirley's album: weddings, birthday party, Austin (2 of 2), circa 1910s-1980s, Includes photos of Shirley Lomax Mansell, Alan Lomax, John Lomax Jr., Bess Lomax Hawes, Corey Hawes, Anna Lomax, Naomi Hawes, John Henry Faulk, Mihalik family members, Chairetakis family members. (Box-folder 36.04)
    - Shirley's album, circa 1970s-1980s, Includes photos of Bess Lomax Hawes, Alan Lomax, John Lomax Jr., Shirley Lomax Mansell, Lisa Gordon, Mihalik family members, Duggan family members, Bishop family members, Corey Hawes. (Box-folder 37.01)
    - Family album, 1948-1978, Includes photos of Naomi Hawes and John Bishop's wedding; Fred Stripp, Corey Denos and Mike Denos, Peter Bishop, Nick Hawes, Jesse Paul Denos, Butch Hawes, Megan Denos, Lisa Gordon, Shirley Lomax Mansell, Ralph Rinzler, Kate Rinzler, Anna Lomax, Bob Jeffrey, Ted Carpenter, Alan Cary, Noah Bishop, Amanda Bishop, Isabelle Hawes, Joshua Hawes (Box-folder 37.02)
    - Oldest family pictures album, circa 1880s-1940s, Includes early photos of Bess Bauman Brown and members of the Brown family, as well photos of Shirley Lomax, John Lomax Jr., Alan Lomax and Bess Lomax in childhood and early adulthood. (Box-folder 38.01)
    - Oversize photographs, circa 1935-1980s, Includes photos of Bess Lomax Hawes as a teenager, and during NEA period; Pete Seeger in 1950s; photos of Butch Hawes sculptures. (Box-folder 39.01)
  - Subseries B: Butch Hawes artwork, Note: Butch Hawes's illustrated version of "The Cowboy and the Wheel," also known as "The Gol-Darned Wheel," was accepted for publication but never published.
    - Sketches, circa 1940s-1960s, Mostly pen and ink and pencil studies of human figure. (Box-folder 40.01)
    - Sketches, circa 1940s-1960s, Mostly pen and ink and pencil studies of human figure and trees; includes notes on cartoon sketches. (Box-folder 40.02)
    - Illustrations in various media, circa 1940s-1960s, Illustrations in pencil, pen and ink and/or paint; includes proof copy of illustration in Young Faces. (Box-folder 40.03)
    - Bird sketches, circa 1940s-1960s, Pencil studies. (Box-folder 40.04)
    - Come visit my ranch, circa 1950, Possibly clippings. (Box-folder 40.05)
    - Prater Violet book jacket, circa 1940s, Proposed design for Christopher Isherwood novel. (Box-folder 40.06)
    - Winter scenes and waiter, circa 1950s-1960s, Illustrations in paint and possibly pen and ink. (Box-folder 40.07)
    - "Look Ma, he did it himself...," circa 1940s-1960s, Pencil drawings, possibly designed as advertisements. (Box-folder 40.08)
    - Young Faces, 1952, Butch Hawes-contributed illustration for "From the gold-darned wheel," in Cowboy Songs by John Lomax, one of 14 folk story fragments that appear in Young Faces: an Illustrated Album of Type Faces for Children's Books (New York: Composing Room, 1952). (Box-folder 40.09)
    - Illustrations, circa 1940s-1960s, Mostly pen and ink or pencil drawings of human figure; includes notes. (Box-folder 41.01)
    - Illustrations, circa 1940s-1960s, "Glossy positive" printed in black ink; western theme. (Box-folder 41.02)
    - Illustration, circa 1950s-1960s, Pencil and paint. (Box-folder 41.03)
    - Woody Guthrie fiddle tunes album design, circa 1940s (Box-folder 41.04)
    - John A. Lomax Jr. portrait, circa 1940s-1960s, Charcoal. (Box-folder 41.05)
    - The Stuff Smith Trio album design, 1944 (Box-folder 41.06)
    - Bagpipes and nurse, circa 1950s-1960s, Painting. (Box-folder 41.07)
    - "The Cowboy and the Wheel" (1 of 13), Cover illustration. (Box-folder 42.01)
    - "The Cowboy and the Wheel" (2 of 13) (Box-folder 42.02)
    - "The Cowboy and the Wheel" (3 of 13) (Box-folder 42.03)
    - "The Cowboy and the Wheel" (4 of 13) (Box-folder 42.04)
    - "The Cowboy and the Wheel" (5 of 13) (Box-folder 42.05)
    - "The Cowboy and the Wheel" (6 of 13) (Box-folder 42.06)
    - "The Cowboy and the Wheel" (7 of 13) (Box-folder 42.07)
    - "The Cowboy and the Wheel" (8 of 13) (Box-folder 42.08)
    - "The Cowboy and the Wheel" (9 of 13) (Box-folder 42.09)
    - "The Cowboy and the Wheel" (10 of 13) (Box-folder 42.10)
    - "The Cowboy and the Wheel" (11 of 13) (Box-folder 42.11)
    - "The Cowboy and the Wheel" (12 of 13) (Box-folder 42.12)
    - "The Cowboy and the Wheel" (13 of 13) (Box-folder 42.13)
- Series IV: Moving images
  - Subseries A: VHS
    - Washington, DC Heritage Festival, 1983 (Tape-id AFC 2014/008: MV01)
    - National Heritage Fellowships, September, 1989, Part I: National Endowment for the Arts Folk Arts Program, Washington, DC (Tape-id AFC 2014/008: MV02)
    - National Heritage Fellowships, September, 1989, Part II: National Endowment for the Arts Folk Arts Program, Washington, DC (Tape-id AFC 2014/008: MV03)
    - National Heritage Fellowships, September, 1993, National Endowment for the Arts Folk Arts Program. (Tape-id AFC 2014/008: MV04)
    - National Heritage Fellows at the Appalachian Stage, 2003, Smithsonian Festival of American Folklife. (Tape-id AFC 2014/008: MV05)
    - Early Years of Public Sector Folklore Forum, 2003, American Folklore Society. (Tape-id AFC 2014/008: MV06)
    - The Fandango Project, undated (Tape-id AFC 2014/008: MV07)
    - Banjo Frolic, undated, Video produced Belgian creators of American five-string banjo exhibit, which was financed by Musical Instruments Museum in Brussels. (Tape-id AFC 2014/008: MV08)
  - Subseries B: DVD
    - The Films of Bess Lomax Hawes, 2003, Georgia Sea Island Singers (1964); Buckdancer (1965); Pizza Pizza Daddy-O (1967); Say Old Man, Can You Play the Fiddle (1970). (Tape-id AFC 2014/008: MV09)
    - The Heritage Awards Ceremony and Concert, September, 2008 (Tape-id AFC 2014/008: MV10)
- Series V: Artifacts
  - NEA Distinguished Service Award, 1987 (Box-folder 43.01)
  - NEA Distinguished Service Award, 1991 (Box-folder 43.02)
  - Bosque County Ballad Hunter, 1994, Includes a small branding iron in the shape of a letter "A." (Box-folder 43.03)
  - CSUN Center for Visual and Performing Arts, 2002, Distinguished Achievement award. (Box-folder 43.04)
  - Topanga Banjo Fiddle Contest Music Legend Award, 2007, "In recognition of a lifetime of dedicated service to the folk and traditional music community." (Box-folder 43.05)
  - Awards, 1970-2004, Collection of awards given to Bess Lomax Hawes by the White House Conference on Children, California State University, Northridge, National Endowment for the Arts, and Smithsonian Institution; also includes award given to filmmaker Bernard Wilets for work on Discovering American Folk Music. (Box-folder 44.01)
  - National Heritage Fellow award template, circa 1982-1992 (Box-folder 44.02)
  - Guam award, 1983, Hawes was named a member of the Ancient Order of the Chammori. (Box-folder 44.03)
  - UNC Chapel Hill doctorate diploma, 1995 (Box-folder 44.04)
  - NEA Certificate of Retirement, 1992 (Box-folder 44.05)
  - Address books and business cards, circa 1960s-1990s, Box includes eight items: two rolodexes and six books containing addresses and business cards. (Box-folder 45)